<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mozilla | Niels Dequeker]]></title>
  <link href="http://voles.github.io/blog/categories/mozilla/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://voles.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-08T19:56:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://voles.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Niels Dequeker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Firefox OS: an introduction]]></title>
    <link href="http://voles.github.io/blog/2013/08/05/firefox-os-an-introduction/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-05T22:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://voles.github.io/blog/2013/08/05/firefox-os-an-introduction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I was invited by <a href="https://twitter.com/remcoder">Remco</a> to join the <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/events/ctdip0rot71j36rrkkl4rkto1p0">Firefox OS event</a> at the <a href="http://q42.com/">Q42</a> office in Amsterdam. It was a great evening. With this blogpost, I’d like to share some of the things I’ve learned.</p>

<p>{% img /images/posts/meetup-firefox-os.JPG %}</p>

<h1>Discussed topics</h1>

<p>Speakers <a href="https://twitter.com/alispivak">Ali Spivak</a> (projectmanager for the Mozilla Developer Network), <a href="https://twitter.com/sergimansilla">Sergi Mansilla</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/janjongboom">Jan Jongeboom</a> (who make software for Firefox OS) gave presentations about Firefox OS, a community-based system for mobile devices.</p>

<p>Besides a general introduction, the two main topics discussed were:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>“What is Firefox OS and who is it targeting?”</em></li>
<li><em>“Why should we / our clients put it on our horizon?”</em></li>
</ul>


<h1>Who is it for?</h1>

<p><a href="http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/os/">Firefox OS</a> is designed for alternative markets. It wants to replace the current feature phones, and give access to smartphones to people who otherwise could not afford it.</p>

<p>A good question was <em>“If you target alternative markets, why don’t you sell the phone in Africa?”</em>.</p>

<p>The answer is that the distribution market is the responsibility of the carriers. They choose where they sell the phone. The phone was recently released in Poland and Hungary.</p>

<h1>Performance</h1>

<p>Most people were actually very curious about the performance, compared to high-end Android devices and the iPhone.</p>

<p>Current low-end devices running Android don’t perform very well at all. Especially if you’re used to work with for example, the iPhone. This is because Android wasn&rsquo;t made to run on these devices.</p>

<p>Because Firefox OS targets these low-end devices, and it is faster than Android, the experience when using Firefox OS is noticeably better.</p>

<p>They brought some devices so we could play around with the OS and see for ourselves. In general, the attendees were quite suprised about how good Firefox OS runs!</p>

<p>{% img /images/posts/meetup-firefox-os-testing.JPG %}</p>

<h1>Standards</h1>

<p>The people behind Mozilla also want to push the usage of standards. This was on one of the slides during the presentation:
{% blockquote %}
“Firefox OS application = website + W3C proposed phone APIs”
{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>That’s great!</p>

<p>The most basic application can actually consist of a single HTML-file. You can style the application with CSS and add extra functionality with JavaScript. They also showed how you can access phone sensors via JavaScript.</p>

<h1>Sensor events</h1>

<p><code>Deviceproximity</code> is an event that allows you to know when something is getting closer or further away from the phone.
An example usecase for this would be to brighten up the screen when a user gets close enough to the phone.</p>

<p><code>Devicelight</code> is an event that gives you access to the amount of light in the room. For example, you can adjust the colors of you paragraphs when it is getting lighter / darker outside.</p>

<p>These are all basic examples, but I’m looking forward to see what others will do with them. The cool thing is that you listen to these events using pure JavaScript!</p>

<h1>Conclusion</h1>

<p>It was nice to get such an extensive introduction to Firefox OS from the masters themselves. There was a lot of Q&amp;A in between, where the thoughts behind the OS were explained very well.</p>

<p>Note: take a look at this slide at the Q42 office!</p>

<p>{% img /images/posts/meetup-firefox-os-slide.JPG %}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
