<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JS | Niels Dequeker]]></title>
  <link href="http://voles.github.io/blog/categories/js/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://voles.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-09T18:48:07+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://voles.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Niels Dequeker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The first JavaScript MVC Meetup]]></title>
    <link href="http://voles.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/amsterdam-javascript-mvc-meetup/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T17:08:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://voles.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/amsterdam-javascript-mvc-meetup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On May 22 we have organized the first JS MVC Meetup in Amsterdam. With this post I'd like to share why we have setup the Meetup, together with some pictures.</p>

<h3>Why organizing a JS MVC specific Meetup</h3>

<p>Last year I've defined the technology stack for <a href="http://social-express.com/">SocialExpress</a>. I found it very hard to choose the right framework for our client application.</p>

<p>At the end I decided to go for AngularJS because of two reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>I had previous experience with AngularJS, which saves time learning something new</li>
<li>it is powered by Google, which adds quite some credibility</li>
</ol>


<p>It was only after talking with <a href="https://twitter.com/tdhulster">Thijs</a> and <a href="http://www.bagu.org/blog/">Ben</a> that I noticed other people also experience the same problem of choosing the right framework for the right purpose.
We knew that there already are quite some JS specific Meetups in Amsterdam, but none of them  focus towards MVC frameworks.</p>

<p>On the first Meetup, we had about 15 people who attended. The talks were about <a href="http://emberjs.com/">EmberJS</a>, <a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> and <a href="http://smacss.com/">SMACSS</a>.</p>

<h3>1. Introduction to Ember and Ember Data</h3>

<p><em>Ben Konrath</em></p>

<p>During his talk Ben introduced some of the key concepts and features in Ember and Ember Data. He shared his experience using these technologies in a large project with an eye towards providing an objective view of the pros and cons of the Ember stack.</p>

<h3>2. SMACSS</h3>

<p><em>Prashant Palikhe</em></p>

<p>Prashant gave a lightning talk on SMACSS, guidelines for scalable &amp; modular CSS architecture that he had used recently in one of his projects.
He shared his learnings with all of us.</p>

<h3>3. Setting up an AngularJS project with Yeoman</h3>

<p><em>Niels Dequeker &amp; Thijs d'Hulster</em></p>

<p>We talked about using Yeoman to quickly setup an AngularJS project. We discussed Yeoman as a workflow, in combination with Grunt and Bower.
On the basis of a demo application, we talked about some of the core concepts of AngularJS, including directives, scopes, etc.</p>

<h2>Some pictures</h2>

<h4>The location</h4>

<p><img src="/images/posts/meetup-location.jpeg" title="'JS MVC Meetup location'" ></p>

<h4>Ben talking about EmberJS</h4>

<p><img src="/images/posts/meetup-ben.jpeg" title="'JS MVC Meetup Ben about EmberJS'" ></p>

<h4>Prashant talking about SMACSS</h4>

<p><img src="/images/posts/meetup-prashant.jpeg" title="'JS MVC Meetup Prashant about SMACSS'" ></p>

<h4>Thijs and me talking about AngularJS</h4>

<p><img src="/images/posts/meetup-thijs-and-niels.jpeg" title="'JS MVC Meetup Niels and Thijs about AngularJS'" ></p>

<h4>Short break</h4>

<p><img src="/images/posts/meetup-break.jpeg" title="'JS MVC Meetup short break'" ></p>

<h2>Room for improvement</h2>

<ul>
<li>Don't change the date once the Meetup is announced, it gives too much confusion</li>
<li>Do more promotion. Talk about our Meetup at other Meetups, flyer, invite friends… This time the only promotion we had was via Meetup.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Final thoughts</h2>

<p>I really enjoyed the evening and it was great to talk with like minded people. During the break I heard about how others projects are organized and which technologies they use for 'bigger' client applications.</p>

<h2>Next Meetup</h2>

<p>The next Meetup is scheduled at June 26. For future Meetups, you can find more information on our <a href="http://www.meetup.com/JavaScript-MVC-Meetup-Amsterdam/">JavaScript MVC Meetup page</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
